Miguel Xochicale

My research interests are in real-time and automatic signal and image processing techniques for AI-based fetal biomechanics.

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences Department of Biomedical Engineering King's College London, UK

A http://mxochicale.github.io/ · in mxochicale

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering

Birmingham, UK

The University of Birmingham

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019. Thesis: 🗷 GitHub: 🖶 Website: 🗹

M.Sc. in Signal Processing

Puebla, México

Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE) Sep 2004 - Sep 2006 Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers 🖾 🖶

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Research Experience

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging at King's College London, UK Sep 2021 – Present

• PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez

· I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python-based and Qt programming languages via GitHub. See more at (2).

Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering at King's College London, UK Apr 2019 – Aug 2021

• PIs: Prof. Tom Vercauteren and Dr. Wenfeng Xia

I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. See more at (2).

Supervision and Teaching Experience

• Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles

King's College London	Jan 2020 – Present
Supervision: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung, MSc in Medical Engineering and Physics	Feb 2021 – Aug 2022
Supervision: Thea Bautista, M. Eng. in Biomedical Engineering	Oct 2021 – May 2022
Supervision: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo and Amal Hussein, Summer projects	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
Supervision: Alexander Mitton, M.Sc. in Medical Engineering and Physics	Jan 2020 – Sep 2020
Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados	Jan 2022 – Apr 2022
Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu	Jan 2021 – Apr 2021

The University of Birmingham

Jun 2018 - Dec 2018

Jan 2020 – Apr 2020

• Supervision: Dinghuang Zhang, M.Sc. in Computer Engineering. Aug 2018 - Dec 2018 Teaching associate: Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony Aug 2017 - Dec 2017; Jan 2018 - Apr2018 Teaching Associate: Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte Jan 2017 - Apr 2017 Teaching Associate Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Aug 2016 - Dec 2016; Aug 2017 - Dec 2017 Teaching Associate: Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber Aug 2016 - Dec 2016

Teaching Associate at Mexican Institutions

Puebla, México

Teaching Associate at Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University, Puebla, México. Aug 2013 - Dec 2013 Jan 2012 - Dec 2012 Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng at Universidad Madero, Puebla, México. Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng. at Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla, Puebla, México. Jan 2007 - Dec 2011

Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng. at Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco, Puebla, México.

Aug 2006 - Jun 2007

Publications

- 1. E. Puyol-Antón, B. Ruijsink, B. S. Sidhu, et al., Ai-enabled assessment of cardiac systolic and diastolic function from echocardiography, Mar. 2022. arXiv: 2203.11726 [physics.med-ph; cs.CV; eess.IV], Full Manuscript.
- 2. A. Badillo-Perez, D. Badillo-Perez, D. Coyotzi-Molina, D. Cruz, R. Montenegro, L. Vazquez, and M. Xochicale, "Piloting diversity and inclusion workshops in artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 17th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '22), Mar. 2022.
- 3. R. Beale, J. B. Rosendo, C. Bergeles, et al., "Oxvent: Design and evaluation of a rapidly-manufactured covid-19 ventilator," eBioMedicine, vol. 76, p. 103868, 2022.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 5. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 6. C. Baker, M. Xochicale, F. Joubert, et al., "Real-time ultrasonic tracking of an intraoperative needle tip with integrated fibre-optic hydrophone," in 2021 IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium (IUS), 2021, pp. 1-4.
- 7. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17), Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 8. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.

- 9. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 10. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 11. **M. Xochicale** and G. Jovanovic-Dolecek, "A new method for design narrow band lowpass fir filters using a scale function," in 2nd International Conference on Electronic Design (ICED '06), Veracruz, Mexico, Nov. 2006, Conference Paper.

Posters

- M. Xochicale, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

Talks

- 1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in *neuromatch* 3.0 (*NMC3 '20*), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

Grants, Awards and Honours

- King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗗 (07/01/2021 07/01/2022)
- My M.Sc. student, Alexander Mitton, won the Outstanding Individual Project award 🗷
- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci (14/04/2020 9/06/2020)
- My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🖸 🔁 🛗
- I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh

 16-18/06/2016
- My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015).
- I won a Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology.
 11/2014-11/2018
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo.
- I won a M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology.

Skills

Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017-present], 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present], Video framegrabbers (e.g. PCI and usb from ephipan), and Medical imaging (e.g. 3D slicer, ITK-SNAP).

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent] and interested in learning Chinese.

Extra Activities

Outreach activities and scientific engagement

• Organising events on behalf of the Early Career Researcher Network at the BMEIS 01-01-2021 - present.

Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering 10-11-2021

• Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM

23-03-2021

Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital 02-2020 – 06-2020

• For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019

For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI.
 99-2019
 Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: and GitHub: 50

• Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🖾, (2016) 🖾, and (2018) 🖾 GitHub: 🖶.

• Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: **6**. 2014–2018

• Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017–2018

• Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter:

**Deair4children GitHub: **B@air4children GitHub: **B@

• Creation Libre Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children. Website: 🗹 2013 – 2017

• Developer of the Website "Machine Learning for México" GitHub: ♂, Website: ♂ 2013 – 2018

09/2004-09/2006